42. The Large Hadron Collider. In Switzerland, in a huge tunnel deep underground, is a giant
scientific instrument. It's called the Large Hadron Collider, LHC. It was built with the
help of more than 10,000 scientists from over 100 different countries to help people learn
more about how our world began. The LHC was built to make different particles collide,
crash into each other, at extremely high speeds. The LHC is so big, 17 miles long,
to allow the particles to build up as much speed as possible. The particles this machine
uses are called hadrons. They're even smaller than atoms. Scientists believe that by smashing
them into each other at high speeds, we can learn more about the Big Bang. The Big Bang
is the name of a theory about how the Earth was formed. The theory guesses that our part
of the universe used to be only a few centimeters of hot space. Then, for some reason, this
space began to expand and cool until it eventually became the vast, cold universe we now have.
Scientists want to know why. The LHC tries to recreate the Big Bang. It spins hadrons
until they are moving at almost the speed of light. The great speed makes them very
hot like they would have been before the Big Bang. Then, when they collide, they produce
a soup of other particles. Scientists are very curious about these other particles.
They believe that studying the beginning of the universe can help them understand how
the universe works now. The LHC will also help scientists try to answer other questions
like what is most of the universe made of and what makes some things have weight. We
don't know if the LHC will actually provide answers, but for now, it's as close as we
can get.